<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble remonstrances of the Commission of the Generall Assemblie, to the Kings Majestie, and Honorable Comittee of Estates, of the third, and twenty fyfth of January, 1651 with the answer from the Kings Majesty &amp; Honorable Comittee of Estates, thereunto, of the sixth of Februarie, 1651.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79735</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18959215</idno>
  <idno type="VID">132918-01</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4229AC</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18959215</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132918-01)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1665:4 or 2552:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble remonstrances of the Commission of the Generall Assemblie, to the Kings Majestie, and Honorable Comittee of Estates, of the third, and twenty fyfth of January, 1651 with the answer from the Kings Majesty &amp; Honorable Comittee of Estates, thereunto, of the sixth of Februarie, 1651.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>Ker, A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Remonstrances signed: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing C4229 on reel 1665; number cancelled in Wing (CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originalS in the British Library and the Glasgow University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  History --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> HUMBLE REMONSTRANCES Of the COMMISSION of the GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERALL ASSEMBLIE, <hi>To the</hi> Kings Majestie, and Honorable Cōmittee of Estates, of the <hi>third, and twenty fyfth of January,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <p>WITH The Answer from the KINGS MAjESTY &amp; <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Cōmittee of Estates, thereunto; of the sixth of Februarie,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDENE;</hi> Printed by James Brown, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="coat_of_arms">
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <p>BON. ACCORD</p>
                  <p>Jnsignia Ʋrbis abredonie,</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="remonstrance">
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:2"/>
            <head>UNTO THE KINGS MOST EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENT MAJESTIE, <hi>AND</hi> To the Honourable Committee <hi>of</hi> ESTATES, The humble REMONSTRANCE of the COMMIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION <hi>of the</hi> GENERALL ASSEMBLIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this sad and calamitous tyme. Wee having called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inhabitants of the Land of all ranks, unto unfeigned repentance, unto a serious search and tryall of their wayes, and turning agayn unto the LORD; And your Honours, having in prosecution of your duetie, according to the Fayth of the Kingdome, and according to the Covenant,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132918-01:3"/>and League and Covenant, solemnelie set the Crown vpon the King, and installed him in the Throne of the Kingdome, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his publick and solemne renewing of the Covenants men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, The conscience of our duetie to GOD, His Kirk, this kingdome, your Majestie, &amp; your Lordships, The desyre to be found faithfull, according to the trust cōmitted to us by the Generall Assemblie, And the care to clear our selves, as in the sight of GOD, before the present generation, and the posteritie that shall come up after us, And before all the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med kirks in the world, That wee haue been, are, and shall be, in the strength of him by whose grace wee stand, affected with all tender respects to the preservation Of the Reformed Religion, by GODS blessing established amongst us, Of the Libertie of this ancient kingdome, and Of the honour and happinesse of his Majestie, in the maintenance of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and liberties of the kingdome, and possessed with a perfect hatred of <hi>Errours</hi> and <hi>Heresias,</hi> Of perfidious compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the maintainers and abbetters thereof, who present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie oppresse a great part, and endevour the enslaving of the whole kingdome, And of treacherous disloyaltie to lawfull authoritie, Have moved us, to represent unto your Honours, the dangers wherewith wee conceave this kingdome for the present to be pressed, and threatned, and the dueties lying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, toward the endevouring the removall, or preventing those apparent evills.</p>
            <p n="1">I. A prevayling enemie within the bowels of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by whom not onlie the persons, and estates of men, but their consciences and soules are in danger to be seduced and destroyed.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Unhappie divisions amongst these that should be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which is a sad prognostick (if not removed) of destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Untymous scrupulositie of manie, in a tyme of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame exigencie, whereby they with-draw themselves, lye by, and refuse to act their duety, which by these that are uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and unacquainted with their tendernesse, will be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132918-01:3"/>a detestable indifferencie, and Neutralitie, an exposing of the Kingdome to the violence of the enemie, and a deserting of the Cause and Covenants.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The perfidious and treacherous compliance of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse, even of such as had trust in the armie, and are now with the enemie.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The desidious neglect of Officers of the Armie, who having diverse thousands, lying in severall partes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the heavie burthen and oppression thereof, and grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the faces of the poore, yet haue not been stirring, and active agaynst the enemie, so much as to disturbe their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters these sixteene weekes by-gone, Though a great part of the Land, hath lyen under the feete of the enemie, looking daylie for reliefe.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The deceatfull <hi>Covetousnesse</hi> of some Officers, who have disappoynted the Leavie of Forces, for Defence of the Kingdome, taking moneyes for men and horses, from the subjects, and yet, not recruiting their companies, according to their receate; by which meanes they have deceaved the Estate, Oppressed the Lieges, mocked the Service, and made up themselves. An intolerable evill, often complayned upon, and yet to this day no effectuall course taken for redresse and remedie.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. The longsome delayes, which are apt to breed jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies into the hearts of the people, that their lurketh some mysterie of iniquitie, which they darre not believe, To enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the spirits of men, and render them faint, and unhappilie to fit them unto a disposition of giving over hopes, and of sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing down under the burthen, and taking on the yoke of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, imposed by the hand of Strangers. In the meane tyme, they are under insupportable sufferinges from the enemie, their persons tyranized over, as bond-slaves, their goods spoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, their meate plucked from their mouthes, their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies readle to sterve for famine, whyle their eyes are fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and lyke to fall out with looking for reliefe, and fynd none.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:132918-01:4"/>
            <p> These evills are so apparent, that nothing needeth to bee spoken for clearing them, it is enough to haue named them: And as wee hope your tender affection to the Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, will constraine you to lay them to heart, and command you to improve all your wit, and strength, with all possible speed and diligence, to search for, apply, and prosecute con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient remedies for these diseases, lest in progresse of tyme, they become incurable; So wee are confident, Your Highnesse and Honours will take it in good part, that wee upon the ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent motives above expressed, have layd them before you, and doe gravelie exhort you, IN THE NAME OF THE MOST HIGH GOD, before whose Tribunall you must stand, to give an accompt unto Him, who is appoynted to judge both great and small.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That Your Majestie, according to the manie and strong engagements that lye upon you, by the solemne incalling upon THE NAME OF GOD in the Covenants, betweene GOD, and You, and the People, And betweene You and Your People, Would approve Your selfe faythfull, in prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ends of these Covenants, in all the heads and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles thereof, for the preservation of Religion, Defence of Your People, administration of Iustice, Your owne personall reformation, the purgation of Your Royall Familie, as of sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from the drosse, And the constituting the same of such as are the faythfull in the Land, And further, that Your Majestie would keep Your selfe from familiaritie, and inteernesse with these who may prove snares to Your Majestie, and give just occasion of offence, to Your Godlie and Honest People, So shall Your Throne be established in Religion and Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; So shall the King rejoyce in GOD, And everie one that sweareth by him, shall glorie, but the mouth of them that speake lyes, shall be stopped, So shall Your Subjects leade a quyet and peaceable lyfe, in all godlinesse, and honestie, under Your Governement: Which, as it hath been the earnest prayer and expectation of us, and all Your People, So shall wee still resolve to importune the Throne of Grace, that You
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132918-01:4"/>may reigne for Him, by whom You reigne, And that above all thinges, You endevour the Well-fare of his Kingdome, who is the exalted Prince, to give salvation unto his people, and who will honour these that honour him, and these that despyse him, shall bee lightlie esteemed.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That laying asyde all selfe interest, as base, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of men that are in places of publick trust, and putting on publick spirits, and bowells of compassion, to the bleeding, and bailefull condition of your mother Kirk, and native King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, you that have been, and are united under the most so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne tyes of Covenants, would cordiallie unite your selfe as one man, serve the LORD with one shoulder, and with one hand, helpe the LORD against the Mightie, for avoyding the curse of <hi>Meroz.</hi> Is it tyme that there should bee stryfe between brethren, when the <hi>Cananites</hi> and <hi>Perizzites</hi> are in the Land? Doeth all the affliction of GODS people seeme light in your eyes? Is it a small thing that the blood of your mothers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren is spilt lyke water upon the ground? Is the Captivitie of <hi>Joseph</hi> quyte forgo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e? Is there no sence of the violence done unto your flesh, in the partes of the Land possessed by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, labouring hardlie, under cruell <hi>Aegyptian</hi> task-masters, despoyled of their goods, and depryved of their daylie bread, and in danger to bee infected with the deadlie poyson of <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous doctrine?</hi> While you that are brethren stryve together, shall the rest of your brethren sterve for want, or enslave them selves for getting bread? Will you suffer your brethren to lye under the hazard of unwholsome food for their soules? Is there no zeale for the LORD, whose Name is blasphemed, His Ordinances trodden under foote, His Covenant contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? If there be anie consolation in CHRIST, if anie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of love, if anie fellowship of the Spirit, and bowells, and mercies, fullfill ye our joye, that ye be lyke mynded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mynd, Let nothing be done through stryfe, or vayne glorie, but in lowlinesse of mynd, Looke not everie one upon his owne thinges, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132918-01:5"/>man also upon the thinges of others, Yea, the thinges of all, the thinges of GOD, of the KIRK, of the KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME, and of the KING, now in COVENANT with GOD, and His KIRK, and in COVENANT also with the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectes in this Kingdome, by their mutuall oathes past at his CORONATION.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That though our present dangers aryse from these, who at the first professed themselves our friendes, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to goe along with us, so long as they might carrie one their owne interest, and dryve their devillish designe, which hath broken foorth to the view of the world, and broken in upon us with an unjust invasion, And daylie bruiseth our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie bones, You would still keepe a watchfull eye over these, who have been from the beginning, and continue still, or are at this tyme obstinate, and professed enemies, and opposers of the COVENANT, and CAUSE of GOD, that none such be put in trust or power, lest the CAUSE of GOD be thereby endangered, and the bitter <gap reason="illegible: page creased" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>te of <hi>Malignancie</hi> spring up, unto the over topping of the tender Vine, which the LORD hath planted amongst us in this Land: Let not the hornes of such grow up unto that longth and strength, as to pusch agayne and pierce the sydes of the People of GOD.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That as with all tendernesse you would compassio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the truelie pious under their doubts and scruples, And en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour, if possiblie, their satisfaction, without prejudice to the CAUSE, So ye would carefullie take heed, that scruple of conscience be not, by some, pretended unto unwillingnesse of of acting, for preservation of the endangered Cause, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Kingdom, and taken on as a mask, to cover the designe of under-hand advancing the interest of the <hi>Sectarian Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> as some have alreadie done, who now unmasking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, are not ashamed to appeare with open face amongst them.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That you would with all wisdome and circumspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132918-01:5"/>in simplicitie of heart, and with myndes disengaged from respect of persons, carefullie endevour, that such as are or shall bee preferred to the keeping of Forts, charge in the Armie, or unto other Places of trust, be men of pietie, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and abilitie for their Imployment, The rather because some have unskillfullie, some unfaythfullie managed, &amp; others treacherouslie betrayed their trust.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That you would declare your zeale, dislyke of, and displeasure agaynst the perfidious, and disnatured countrey men, who joyne themselves with the common enemie, who are haters of ZION, and of this Nation, who say, <hi>Let us roote out their name from under Heaven;</hi> as also agaynst compliars with them, according to the degree, and qualitie of their offence.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That some censure may be inflicted upon these Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that through base <hi>Covetousnesse,</hi> and shamelesse love of money, which is the roote of all evill, have filled their owne handes, and not increassed their Forces; And some solid course may be taken, for preventing the lyke disappoyntment of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, and unnecessarie oppression of the people, in tyme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: And, because there are manie oppressions, and insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, acted by souldiours, You would bee pleased to cause ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise Militarie Discipline, exactlie, according to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Warre, whereby they may bee restrayned from the lyke practises.</p>
            <p>AND LASTLIE, That You would vigorouslie goe about the acting of some what in opposition to the enemie, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the losse of so much tyme, and manyfold opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Be of good cowrage, and play the Men for Your People, and for the Cities of Your GOD, and let the LORD doe what seemeth Him good. The just eye of the Righteous judge of the World, who is a swift Witnesse agaynst all that sweare falslie by His NAME, beholdeth all Your beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, His Eyes runne to and fro, to show Himselfe strong for them, whose hearts are perfect towardes Him. The eyes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132918-01:6"/>of all the Reformed KIRKS are upon you, to observe your actions, whether you quyte your selves lyke faythfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, Good Patriots, and Loyall Subjects, towards your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed Religion, your Native Kingdome, and your crowned King, in Covenant with the People of GOD, according to the manyfold Obligations of the Nationall Covenant, League and Covenant, and other solemne Oathes, wherby you are engaged. Thinke not that you shall escape more then others, for if you shall altogether with-holde your hand at this tyme Then shall there enlargement &amp; delyverance arise from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, but you &amp; your Families will be ruined. Commit your wayes unto the LORD, and goe on in the power of His Might, with your lyves in your handes, Entering upon duetie, attended by danger, with ESTHERS magnanimous resolution, IF WE PERISH, WE PERISH. The GOD of Heaven shall accept of your endevours, and in Him wee trust, that Hee shall second them with happie successe; Your reward is with Him, and your names shall be precious to the present and succeeding Generation, Because you devoted your selves for preserving and transmitting inteere, what ever is, and ought to bee in highest esteeme with men, that are not voyde of Religion, reason, and naturall affection. The onlie Wyse GOD, The King Eternall, Immortall, Invisible, give unto Your Highnesse, and to Your Honours, Understanding in all thinges; And let the Beautie of the LORD our GOD bee upon you, And establish the work of your handes; yea, the worke of your handes may hee establish.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="remonstrance">
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:6"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Andrewes, <date>25 January, 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>To the King his most Excellent <hi>Majestie, And the Honourable</hi> Committee of Estates, The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Remonstrance of the Commission of the Generall Assemblie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the present sad distresses of this KIRK, and Kingdome, and the imminent danger of greater calamities threatned daily against the same, by the publick enemie, and readie shortly to overwhelm them, if not speedily prevented, requyre rather that your Majestie and Lordships should be whollie and activelie taken up, in setting all lawfull and necessarie meanes on foote, for defence and delyverance of the Land, and people of GOD therein, from oppression and bondage, then to be anie wayes diverted by papers from anie; And we would be loath to trouble you with any thing of this kynd, having of late in severall Remonstrances, been represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such matters as we found needfull, and incumbent to us, to hold forth, for the good of the Kirk &amp; Kingdom: Yet conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the trust that is committed to us, in relation to publick ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, for discharging of which we must answer to GOD &amp; the Kirk; And perceaving sundry things in the present publick car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of busines, which we conceave may prove justly offensive to honest people, and very prejudiciall to the work; As it is our duety; So we hope it shall never offend you, nor any way retard: But shall further acting for the publick good; that we doe use our wonted freedom and faithfulnes, in representing at this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132918-01:7"/>tyme to your Majestie and Lordships some of these thinges, which especiallie need tymouslie to be looked to, &amp; remedied.</p>
            <p>And first, That whereas in answer to the Quaeree, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by your Majestie &amp; the Estates of Parliament, we did give our faithfull advyce concerning such persons, as might in the present necessity, be lawfully imployed in service, for defence of the kingdom, against the publick enemy: We doe perceave, that in the Act of Leavie, some persons are nominat to be Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in Regiments, who are under the limitations &amp; exceptions expressed in that our answer, &amp; insert in the Act of Leavie; As also we are informed that sundry under Officers are chosen by Collonels in Shyres, who having been formerly under censure, have not as yet satisfied the Kirk: We do humbly conceave, that it had been fit, rather to have kept within the bounds of the exceptions, so farre as necessity could have permitted, then to have transgressed &amp; gone beyond them: And now we doe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly beseech your Majesty &amp; Lordships, that this may be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to, &amp; remedied in tyme; and that you would, both for your selfes rectifie what is amisse of this kynd in the Act of Leavie, &amp; and also take effectuall course, that Collonels in Shyres doe not choose vnder Officers, who have not given satisfaction to the Kirk, and that such as are of this condition, and are already put in command, may be removed. There is not want of Officers in the kingdome, able for charge, against whom there can be no just exception; And we cannot but heavily regrate, that, as we are informed, many such are passed by, and others imployed.</p>
            <p>In the next place, We desyre in all humilitie, to represent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Majestie &amp; Lordships, our sad fears, concerning the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent slow progresse that is in publick proceedings, towards acting against the enemy: A great part of the kingdom is lying under miserable bondage, &amp; only not utterly destroyed, &amp; past recovery: The rest threatned with the lyke calamities by the enemy, who is diligent &amp; active every way, for accomplishing his designs; all thinges deare to us in the world are lying at the stake, yet it is a wonder, and a matter of very great fear to the people generally, that not only here-to-fore since the sad defare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132918-01:7"/>at <hi>Dumbar,</hi> for so long a time, so litle hath been effectually indevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the reliefe of the Land, and that publick courses formerlie appointed for gathering Forces together, have been rendered in effectual, by particular mens grosse interverting them to their own privat gaine: But that also since our resolution to the Quaeree you propounded to us, in poynt of conscience, concerning a new Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, the orders issued foorth by your Majestie and the Estates of Parliament for the Leavie, have been followed with so slender dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and execution, that it is lyke, the enemie may have faire oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to over-runne all, ere there be any considerable power to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose him. We wil not, nor can we say, but much of the Cause herof is abroad through the countrey, in the basenesse &amp; aversnes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to put themselves to present trouble, though for the defence of their countrey, Religion, Lyves &amp; Liberties; yet we must earnestly and humbly desyre, it be carefully looked to, that the retarding of proceedings, doe not in part, aryse from the fountayne of actings it selfe. We shall be farre from blaming anie in particular: But we think surelie, that were there more activitie &amp; forwardnesse there, there needed not be so much slownesse abroad in the countrey. Therefore wee beseech your Majestie and Lordships, by all these bondes of nature, Religion, Vowes, and Covenants, and Honour, that lye upon you before GOD, and the World, that you would see to the discoverie, and removing of all obstructions, which may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard, and for slow proceedings, according to publick resolutions: And that you would both activelie bestirre your selfs, as also, by that Power and Authoritie which GOD hath put in your handes, cause all others doe their duetie according to their places and sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for Defence and delyverie of this bleeding and perishing Countrey and Kingdome: That you may not, through slacknesse, or anie other way, bring upon your selfes the guilt of destroying the same, nor that Curse which posteritie would have just cause to imprecate upon this Generation, if through our default, they should be made slaves to so wicked usurpers.</p>
            <p>Wee have for the present but this to adde in the last place, that as we lyked well of the Answer given by your Lordships to our Remonstrance to the Parliament of the date
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132918-01:8"/>So we are very sory we doe not as yet see performances answerable thereunto, Especially in the matter cōcerning these, that in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Leavie tooke up money for men and horses, through the countrey; As this was a most vyle wickednesse, and a very betraying of the Cause, and Kingdome; So it is a thing most offensive to all people within the Land, that here-to-fore nothing hath been effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuallie done for calling these men to an accompt: For how-so-ever a Committee was appoynted for their tryall, yet what hath that Committee done? And how commeth it to passe, that they have done nothing? Wee will not determine whence the obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this matter hath flowed; But certaynlie if your Lordships doe not take some effectuall course to try and redresse that vyle abusing of the countrey; you will bring the guilt of it upon your selfes, incowrage all covetous persons in place, to be still practising in that same way, and cannot but make people unwilling to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie publick duetie, as seeing that themselves are but exhausted, to make up private men, and no course taken for preventing anie abuses in this kynd. GOD forbid your MAjESTIE and LORDSHIPS should connive at, and passe over such wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse.</p>
            <p>The great necessitie of this Kingdome, conscience of our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and desyre to be faythfull in our Places to your MAjESTIE and LORDSHIPS constrayned us to use this humble Freedome, which wee trust will bee taken in good part. ARYSE, FOR THIS MATTER BELONGETH UNTO YOU: TAKE COWRAGE, AND DOE IN YOUR STATIONS AND PLACBS.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:8"/>
            <head>PERTH, 6. Febr. 1651.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He KINGS MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIE, and COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITTEE of ESTATES, doe take well, and return heartie thanks to the COMMISSIONERS of the GENERALL ASSEMBLIE, for their care, and faythfulnesse, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving frequent, and seasonable WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NINGS of these dueties, which ought to bee Performed for the good of Religion, King, &amp; Kingdom: And that they may the better resolve, and provyde Remedie, that none bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have Charge in the Armie, but such as are capable, according to the advyce given by the Commission in their ANSWERE to the QUAEREE propounded, by the KING and Parliament, They desyre they will condiscend particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie upon such Persons, as are not capable of imployment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that advyce, And doe further desyre you to make knowne to the Commissioners of the Generall Assemblie, that by Act of Parliament, and of this Committee, It is ordayned, That none against whom there is exception, shall bee admitted to exerce anie Charge in the Armie, till first they had satisfied the Kirk; And desyre to be informed of anie the Commissioners of the Kirk doe know of that kynd, for it is the Resolution of the Committee to admit of none, till they give satisfaction, &amp; when they hear of any, to remove them, till satisfaction be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And as for punishing of such as have taken money for men, there is a select Committee appoynted, which daylie sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, &amp; are proceeding with al the care they can, for trying such as are guilty of that fault: And where they can get Probation, resolve to inflict condign punishmēt upō such as are guilty; But have cause to expostulat that not-with-standing the frequent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132918-01:9"/>advertisements given to the Cōmittees of Warre, there is great slownes, and aversnes to bring in either Complaint, or Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion agaynst anie. And that there hath not been effectuall means, for raising of Forces, &amp; acting against the Enemy, for reliefe of the kingdom, since the dissipating of the Army at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> The same hath not proceeded from want of frequent advertisements, and peremptory orders, from the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, the Parliament, and Committee of Estates, to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of Warre, and Collonels of the severall Shyres, from tyme to tyme, showing them, the imminent dangers, and requyring them to speedy performance of their duetie, as will appeare, &amp; bee made evident, by the many letters &amp; orders sent to them For that effect; But from the slownesse, and aversnesse of the Countrey. And wee cannot but with regrate desyre to make known to the Commissioners of the Generall Assemblie, that the difference of Iudgement of some of the Ministerie, from the Publick Resolutions of the King, and Parliament, and Commissioners of the Generall Assemblie; And their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to concurre, and hindering their People, to give obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Orders, is not one of the least obstructions to the Leavie, and acting against the Enemie, Which his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and Committee, doe earnestlie desyre may by the wisdome of the Commissioners of the Generall Assemblie bee tymelie remedied; Wherein his Majestie, and this Committee, are most willing, and desyreous to contribute their best advyce, and assistance; And have appoynted some of their number, to conferre with the Commissioners of the Generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, at their ensuing Meeting at PERTH. EXTRACT.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Tho: Henderson.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132918-01:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>